Guide to the Gurney Harriss Kearns Papers, 1913-1970
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Gurney Harriss Kearns papers 1913-1970
Kearns, Gurney Harriss, 1872-1962
12 linear feet Extent: 4,106 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.00770
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The papers of Gurney Harriss Kearns, a textile manufacturer, were a gift to the Rubenstein Library in 1977 by Crown Hosiery Mills, High Point, N.C.
Biographical Note
1872 Gurney Harriss Kearns born Sept. 12 on family farm in Guilford County near High Point, N.C.
1890s Attended Trinity College, later Duke University
1900 Associated with brother Oscar E. Kearns to establish Kearns Furniture Co., High Point
1906 Married Katherine Whittier Ragan of High Point
1913 Founded Crown Hosiery Mills at High Point
1934 Became trustee of High Point College
1935 Initiated Gurney Harriss Kearns Fellowship in Religion at Duke University for graduate study
1951 Endowment at Duke University increased to $100,000 as the Gurney Harriss Kearns Foundation for Graduate Study in Religion
1960 Became trustee emeritus of High Point College
1962 Died November 19 at High Point
Collection Overview
The papers of Gurney Harriss Kearns (1872-1962) date primarily during 1913-1962 but include items as late as 1970. There are eight series: Information; Correspondence; Everett, Zane and Muse; American Trust Company; Duke University; High Point College; Miscellaneous; and Crown Hosiery Mills. The collection relates mostly to the operations of Crown Hosiery Mills and to Kearns' real estate investments, membership on the board of directors of High Point College, and his endowment of fellowships at Duke University for graduate study in religion. Numerous references to his immediate family appear in various letters. There are occasional references to the Methodist Church, especially to Wesley Memorial at High Point of which Kearns was a member.
The Information Series contains reference material about Gurney H. Kearns, his family, and Crown Hosiery Mills.
The Correspondence Series (1959 items) contains the incoming letters and copies of the outgoing letters of Gurney H. Kearns during 1923-1963. Most of the correspondence from June, 1927, to April, 1931, is missing, and the quantity declines after 1943. The principal topic is Kearns' personal financial business. References to Crown Hosiery Mills are scarce. During 1923-1927 Kearns' real estate investments are the predominant topic. They include buildings, apartments, rental property, land and related transactions with real estate agents and insurance companies. Activity was considerable in North Carolina, especially in Greensboro and High Point, but also elsewhere, notably in Washington, D.C., and during 1926-1927 in Florida. During 1931-1943 the Depression's effects are evident, as Kearns' business is more concerned with managing debts, loans, and property than with acquisition. After 1943 the letters relate more to personal and family matters. Items of note concern Oak Ridge Institute (1925-1926), Springfield Friends Church (Dec. 18, 1936), Concord Methodist Church in Randolph Co. and Methodist churches in High Point (1937), church indebtedness in the Western N.C. Conference (Nov. 17, 1938), and Christianity and business (May 22, 1938).
The Everett, Zane and Muse Series (450 items) contains their letters to Gurney H. Kearns and copies of his replies during 1932-1952. Everett, Zane and Muse, an accounting firm located in Greensboro, N.C., handled business for both Crown Hosiery Mills and for Kearns personally, and the correspondence represents both interests. There are references to a variety of loan, tax, insurance, property, accounting, and other legal and financial matters. Many of the same transactions can be found in the Correspondence Series.
The American Trust Company Series (196 items) consists of their letters to Kearns and copies of his replies during 1939-1944. The American Trust Company, a bank in Charlotte, N.C., handled business for both Crown Hosiery Mills and for Kearns and other members of his family. The principal topics are loans and related insurance and property matters. These letters are sometimes more informative about transactions than the correspondence with Everett, Zane and Muse. There are occasional references to economic conditions.
The Duke University Series (1066 items), 1931-1965, contains Kearns' incoming and outgoing correspondence, mostly 1935-1962, with faculty, officials, graduate students, alumni, and doctors at the University, and others. The principal topic is the endowment that he established in the Graduate School of Arts and Sciences for the support of graduate students in religion, especially those preparing to become college and seminary teachers. In 1935 Kearns began the Gurney Harriss Kearns Fellowship in Religion that was expanded in 1951 into the Gurney Harriss Kearns Foundation for Graduate Study in Religion with an endowment of $100,000. At the time of Kearns' death in 1962 there had been 62 Kearns Fellows. The correspondence concerns the founding and development of the endowment, the property supporting it, the Kearns Fellows, the Department of Religion, the Divinity School, Duke University, Kearns' church, and the churches and schools where some of the former Kearns Fellows located. The principal correspondent, 1935-1962, is Dr. H Shelton Smith, James B. Duke Professor of American Religious Thought. Other correspondents include Kearns Fellows, doctors whom Kearns consulted at Duke Hospital, businessmen involved with the endowment property, and various officials of the University, especially President Robert Lee Flowers in the 1930s and 1940s.
The High Point College Series (304 items) concerns this Methodist school where Kearns was a trustee from 1934 until he retired to emeritus status in 1960. The files include primarily letters to and from Kearns and officials of the college and minutes, reports, and memoranda from its board of trustees and subordinate committees. There is considerable information about fund raising, finances, development, and administration. Correspondents include Gideon I. Humphreys, president in the 1940s and a continuing correspondent, Dennis Hargrove Cooke, president in the 1950s, Wendell Melton Patton who assumed the office in 1959, trustees, and occasionally faculty and other persons. The papers are minimal before 1942, limited during most of the 1940s, and relatively numerous during 1949-1959.
The Miscellaneous Series contains a ledger, 1919-1935, for Gurney H. Kearns' personal finances. There is also a folder of letters and printed material, 1939-1960, concerning Wesley Memorial Methodist Church in High Point, including a sermon by its minister opposing the election of John F. Kennedy to the presidency because he was a Roman Catholic.
The Crown Hosiery Mills Series consists of minutes, financial papers, and extensive account books. The minutes (photocopies), 1913-1935, also include records of stock issued, 1913-1929, and dividends, 1916-1931. The financial papers, 1935-1939 and 1947, are varied and not numerous, but they contain some useful data. There are 94 account books including: the ledger, 1913-1917; inventories, 1913-1936; and trial balances, 1921-1933; index and profit and loss accounts 1921-1947; cashbooks, 1913-1921, including trial balances, 1934-1944; cash journals, 1921-1950; time books and payroll, 1913-1934; payroll, 1922-1927; order books for labels, bands, riders, and transfers, 1926-1930; sales commission book, 1937-1949; and voucher records, 1913-1921. These volumes include the earliest ledger and journal. Later ones are absent, but some summary figures can be found in the trial balances and in the profit and loss accounts. The time books and payroll provide names of employees, hours worked, and wages paid during the first two decades of the mill's operation.
Subject Headings
Hosiery industry -- North Carolina; Real property; Insurance, property; Banks and banking; Endowments -- North Carolina; Accountants -- North Carolina; Textile workers -- North Carolina; High Point College (High Point, N.C.); Duke University. Dept. of Religion; Methodist Episcopal Church, South -- North Carolina; Kearns family; Industries -- North Carolina; American Trust Company (Charlotte, N.C.); Everett, Zane and Muse (Greensboro, N.C.); Crown Hosiery Mills (High Point, N.C.); Smith, H. Shelton (Hilrie Shelton), 1893-
Contents of Collection
- Information Series
  Reference material about Gurney H. Kearns, his family, and Crown Hosiery Mills.
  - Reference Material (Box 1)
- Correspondence Series (Box 1)
  Kearns' incoming and outgoing letters primarily relating to his personal financial business, especially real estate. Arranged chronologically.
  - 1923, Jan.-Dec. (Box 1)
  - 1924, Jan.-May (Box 1)
  - 1924, June-Aug. (Box 1)
  - 1924, Sept.-Dec. (Box 1)
  - 1925, Jan.-June (Box 1)
  - 1925, July-Dec. (Box 1)
  - 1926, Jan.-March (Box 1)
  - 1926, April-June (Box 1)
  - 1926, July-Sept. (Box 1)
  - 1926, Oct.-Dec. (Box 2)
  - 1927, Jan.-May and 1927 (Box 2)
  - 1930, Dec.; 1931, May-Dec., 1932, Jan.-Nov. (Box 2)
  - 1932, Jan.-Dec. (Box 2)
  - 1934, Jan.-Dec. (Box 2)
  - 1935, Jan.-Dec. (Box 2)
  - 1936, Jan.-Dec. (Box 2)
  - 1937, Jan.-June (Box 2)
  - 1937, July-Dec. (Box 2)
  - 1938, Jan.-June (Box 2)
  - 1938, July-Dec. (Box 2)
  - 1939, Jan.-Dec. (Box 3)
  - 1940, Jan.-Dec. (Box 3)
  - 1941, Jan.-Dec. (Box 3)
  - 1942, Jan.-Dec. (Box 3)
  - 1943, Jan.-Dec. (Box 3)
  - 1944, Jan.-1949, Dec. (Box 3)
  - 1950, Jan.-1957, Dec. (Box 3)
  - 1958, Feb.-1963, June (Box 3)
  - undated (Box 3)
- Everett, Zane and Muse Series (Box 3)
  Kearns' correspondence with this Greensboro accounting firm concerning both his personal business and Crown Hosiery Mills. Arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence (Box 3)
    - 1932, Oct.-1937, Dec. (Box 3)
    - 1938, Jan.-June (Box 3)
    - 1938, July-Dec. (Box 3)
    - 1939, Jan.-Dec. (Box 4)
    - 1940, Jan.-Dec. (Box 4)
    - 1941, Jan.-Dec. (Box 4)
    - 1942, Jan.-1952, June (Box 4)
- American Trust Company Series (Box 4)
  Kearns' correspondence with this Charlotte bank that handled business for him and Crown Hosiery Mills. Arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence (Box 4)
    - 1936, Nov.-1938, Dec. (Box 4)
    - 1939, Jan.-1940, Dec. (Box 4)
    - 1941, Jan.-1944, May (Box 4)
- Duke University Series (Box 4)
  Kearns' correspondence about the fellowships that he endowed for the support of graduate study in religion. Includes faculty, officials, graduate students, alumni, and doctors at the University. Arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence (Box 4)
    - 1931, May-1937, Dec. (Box 4)
    - 1938, Jan.-Dec. (Box 4)
    - 1939, Jan.-Dec. (Box 4)
    - 1940, Jan.-Dec. (Box 4)
    - 1941, Jan.-Dec. (Box 4)
    - 1942, Jan.-Dec. (Box 5)
    - 1943, Jan.-Dec. (Box 5)
    - 1944, Jan.-Dec. (Box 5)
    - 1945, Jan.-Dec. (Box 5)
    - 1946, Jan.-Dec. (Box 5)
    - 1947, Jan.-Dec. (Box 5)
    - 1948, Jan.-Oct. (Box 5)
    - 1949, May-Dec. (Box 5)
    - 1950, Jan.-1951, Dec. (Box 5)
    - 1952, Jan.-Dec. (Box 5)
    - 1953, Jan.-1954, Dec. (Box 5)
    - 1956, Sept.-19-57, Dec. (Box 5)
    - 1958, Jan.-April (Box 5)
    - 1958, May-Dec. (Box 5)
    - 1959, Jan.-Dec. (Box 6)
    - 1960, Jan.-Dec. (Box 6)
    - 1961, Jan.-Dec. (Box 6)
    - 1962, April-1965, March (Box 6)
- High Point College Series (Box 6)
  Correspondence, minutes, reports, and memoranda associated with Kearns' work as a trustee. Arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence (Box 6)
    - 1934, June-1945, Dec. (Box 6)
    - 1946, Jan.-1947, Nov. (Box 6)
    - 1949, June-Dec. (Box 6)
    - 1950, Jan.-May (Box 6)
    - 1950, June-Dec. (Box 6)
    - 1951, Jan.-June (Box 6)
    - 1951, July-Dec. (Box 6)
    - 1952, Jan.-Dec. (Box 6)
    - 1953, Jan.-April (Box 7)
    - 1954-1957 (Box 7)
    - 1958, May-Dec. (Box 7)
    - 1959, Jan.-May (Box 7)
    - 1959, July-Dec. (Box 7)
    - 1960, Jan.-Oct. (Box 7)
    - 1961, April; 1970 (Box 7)
- Miscellaneous Series (Box 7)
  Kearns' personal ledger and material relating to Wesley Memorial Methodist Church.
  - Gurney Harriss Kearns' Ledger, 1919-1935 (Box 7)
  - Wesley Memorial Methodist Church, 1939-1960 (Box 7)
- Crown Hosiery Mills Series (Box 7)
  Ledger, journal, balance sheets, inventories, trial balances, profit and loss accounts, cashbooks, cash journals, time books, voucher records, order book, and sales commission book. Also minutes and financial papers. Volumes arranged chronologically by type.
  - Minutes, 1913-1935 (Including Stock Issued, 1913-1929, and Dividends, 1916-1931) (Box 7)
  - Financial Papers, 1935-1939, 1947 (Box 7)
  - Account Books (Box 7)
    - Ledger, 1913-1917 (Volume 1, Box 7)
    - Journal, 1913, July-1921, March (Volume 2, Box 7)
    - Balance Sheets, 1913, Dec.-1932, Dec.,and Inventories, 1913, Dec.-1936, Dec. (Volume 3, Box 7)
    - Trial Balances, 1921, Jan.-1933, Nov. (Box 7)
    - Index and Profit and Loss Accounts, 1921-1947 (Volume 4, Box 7)
    - Cashbook, 1913, Aug.-1920, June (Volume 5, Box 7)
    - Cashbook, 1920, July-1921, March (Volume 6, Box 7)
    - Trial Balances, 1934, Jan.-1944, Nov. (Box 7)
    - Cash Journal, 1921, Jan.-1922, Oct. (Volume 7, Box 7)
    - Cash Journal, 1922, Nov.-1925, Oct. (Volume 8, Box 7)
    - Cash Journal, 1925, Oct.-1927, Aug. (Volume 9, Box 7)
    - Cash Journal, 1927, Sept.-1929, April (Volume 10, Box 7)
    - Cash Journal, 1929, April-1930, Sept. (Volume 11, Box 7)
    - Cash Journal, 1930, Sept.-1932, April (Volume 12, Box 7)
    - Cash Journal, 1932, May-1933, Dec. (Volume 13, Box 7)
    - Cash Journal, 1933, Dec.-1935, Jan. (Volume 14, Box 7)
    - Cash Journal, 1935, Feb.-1937, May (Volume 15, Box 7)
    - Cash Journal, 1937, June-1939, June (Volume 16, Box 7)
    - Cash Journal, 1939, July-1941, Feb. (Volume 17, Box 7)
    - Cash Journal, 1941, March-1942, Sept. (Volume 18, Box 7)
    - Cash Journal, 1942, Oct.-1944, April (Volume 19, Box 7)
    - Cash Journal, 1944, May-1945, Dec. (Volume 20, Box 7)
    - Cash Journal, 1945, Dec.-1947, Aug. (Volume 21, Box 7)
    - Cash Journal, 1947, Aug.-Nov. (Volume 22, Box 7)
    - Cash Journal, 1947, Dec.-1948, March (Volume 23, Box 7)
    - Cash Journal, 1948, March-July (Volume 24, Box 7)
    - Cash Journal, 1948, July-Nov. (Volume 25, Box 7)
    - Cash Journal, 1948, Nov.-1949, March (Volume 26, Box 7)
    - Cash Journal, 1949, April-Aug. (Volume 27, Box 7)
    - Cash Journal, 1949, Aug.-1950, March (Volume 28, Box 7)
    - Cash Journal, 1950, March-July (Volume 29, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1913, Aug.-1914, March (Volume 30, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1914, March-Dec. (Volume 31, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1914, Dec.-1915, Sept. (Volume 32, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1915, Sept.-1916, May (Volume 33, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1916, May-Dec. (Volume 34, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1916, Dec.-1917, June (Volume 35, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1917, June-Dec. (Volume 36, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1917, Dec.-1918, June (Volume 37, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1918, June-Dec. (Volume 38, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1918, Dec.-1919, July (Volume 39, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1919, July-Aug. (Volume 40, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1919, Aug.-1920, May (Volume 41, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1920, May-1921, April (Volume 42, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1921, May-Nov. (Volume 43, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1921, Nov.-1922, May (Volume 44, Box 7)
    - Time Book- and Payroll, 1922, May-Nov. (Volume 45, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1922, Nov.-1923, May (Volume 46, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1923, May-Nov. (Volume 47, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1923, Nov.-1924, June (Volume 48, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1924, June-Nov. (Volume 49, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1924, Nov.-1925, March (Volume 50, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1925, March-June (Volume 51, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1925, June-Oct. (Volume 52, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1925, Oct.-1926, Jan. (Volume 53, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1926, Jan.-April (Volume 54, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1926, April-July (Volume 55, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1926, Aug.-Nov. (Volume 56, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1926, Nov.-1927, Feb. (Volume 57, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1927, Feb.-May (Volume 58, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1927, May-Aug. (Volume 59, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1927, Aug.-Nov. (Volume 60, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1927, Nov.-1928, Feb. (Volume 61, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1928, Feb.-May (Volume 62, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1928, May-July (Volume 63, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1928, July-Oct. (Volume 64, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1928, Oct.-Dec. (Volume 65, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll,1929.Jan.-April (Volume 66, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1929, April-June (Volume 67, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1929, July-Sept. (Volume 68, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1929, Sept.-Dec. (Volume 69, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1929, Dec.-1930, Feb. (Volume 70, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1930, Feb.-May (Volume 71, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1930, May-Aug. (Volume 72, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1930, Aug.-Nov. (Volume 73, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1930, Nov.-1931, Feb. (Volume 74, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1931, March-June (Volume 75, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1931, June-Sept. (Volume 76, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1931, Sept.-Dec. (Volume 77, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1931, Dec.-1932, March (Volume 78, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1932, March-July (Volume 79, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1932, July-Oct. (Volume 80, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1932, Oct.-1933, Jan. (Volume 81, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1933, Jan.-April (Volume 82, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1933, April-Aug. (Volume 83, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1933, Aug.-Nov. (Volume 84, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1933, Nov.-1934, Feb. (Volume 85, Box 7)
    - Time Book and Payroll, 1934, Feb.-July (Volume 86, Box 7)
    - Payroll, 1922, July-1925, May (Volume 87, Box 7)
    - Payroll, 1925, May-1927, Oct. (Volume 88, Box 7)
    - Order Book for Labels, Bands, Riders, and Transfers, 1926-1930 (Volume 89, Box 7)
    - Sales Commission Book, 1937-1949 (Volume 90, Box 7)
    - Voucher Record, 1913, March-1915, Sept. (Volume 91, Box 7)
    - Voucher Record, 1915, Oct.-1917, Oct. (Volume 92, Box 7)
    - Voucher Record, 1917, Nov.-1919, Oct. (Volume 93, Box 7)
    - Voucher Record, 1919, Nov.-1921, March (Volume 94, Box 7)